Guide to the Alfred Edward Housman Correspondence
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Alfred Edward Housman Correspondence
1922-1958.
Housman, A. E. (Alfred Edward), 1859-1936,
157 items (2 boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078912
Biographical Note
English poet, classical Latin scholar. A.E. Housman's brother was Laurence Housman (1865-1959), a poet and playwright.
Scope and Content
Correspondence by and relating to Housman and to his brother, Laurence Housman. Nearly all of the letters were written to Cyril Clemens, who was working on a proposed biography of A.E. Housman. The collection includes six letters from A.E. Housman and an important group of 94 letters from Laurence Housman, which contain comments on his brother's life and activities, religious beliefs, reading, and manuscripts. There are 45 letters from relatives and persons closely related to A.E. Housman, among them his sisters, Clemence Housman and Katharine E. Symons, his publisher, Grant Richards, and his associates at Oxford University, James T. Nance and Alfred W. Pollard. Also included in the collection are twelve manuscripts, the most noteworthy of which are two signed poems by Laurence Housman and a 4-line verse in Lord Dunsany's holograph entitled "A. E. Housman."
Subjects
University of Oxford.; Housman, Laurence, 1865-1959.; Clemens, Cyril, 1902-; Housman, Clemence.; Symons, Katharine E.; Richards, Grant, 1911-1963.; Nance, James T.; Pollard, Alfred W. (Alfred William), 1859-1944.; Dunsany, Edward John Moreton Drax Plunkett, Baron, 1878-1957.; England--Religious life and customs.; Families--England.; Dramatists, English.; Literature publishing--England.; English literature--20th century.; Publishers and publishing--England.; Scholarly publishing.; Poems.; Poets, English.; Poets, English.; Classicists.
Acquisition
1963 M-63 Melville, Ward Gift in memory of Frederick Coykendall
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Subseries I.1: A. Letters of A. E. Housman (6)
    - 6 letters from A.E.H. to Cyril. Clemens, 1927-34 (Box 1)
  - Subseries I.2: B. Letters of Laurence Housman (94)
    - 94 letters from L.H, mostly to Cyril Clemens, but including a few to others, 1922-58 (Box 1)
  - Subseries I.3: C. Other letters (45)
    - 3 letters, E.H. Blakeney to Cyril Clemens, 1937 (Box 1)
    - 1 letter, L.P. Brown to Cyril Clemens, 1937 (Box 1)
    - 1 letter, R. Gleadowe to [Cyril Clemens?), 1936 (Box 1)
    - 1 letter,W.H. Hamilton to Cyril. Clemens, 1936 (postcard) (Box 1)
    - 1 letter, E.S.P. Haynes to Cyril Clemens, 1937 (Box 1)
    - 1 letter, Robert Hillyer to Cyril Clemens, 1936 (Box 1)
    - 1 letter, E. O. Hoppe to Cyril Clemens, 1936 (Box 1)
    - 2 letters, Clemence Housman (sister of A. E. H.) to Cyril Clemens, 1936 and 1943 (letter is a postcard) (Box 1)
    - 1 letter, Anita Loos to Cyril. Clemens, no date [December 7, 19361) (Box 2)
    - 1 letter, Leonard Mackall. to Cyril Clemens, 1936 (Box 2)
    - 6 letters, J. T. Nance to Cyril Clemens, 1936-37 (Box 2)
    - 1 letter, Henry W. Nevinson to Cyril Clemens, 1936 (Box 2)
    - 1 letter, A. W. Pollard to Cyril Clemens, 1937 (Box 2)
    - 1 letter, A. L. (?) Poole to Cyril Clemens, 1936 (Box 2)
    - 7 letters, Grant Richards to A. E. Housman, 1898-1904 (Box 2)
    - 2 letters, Grant Richards to Cyril Clemens, 1936+1942 (Box 2)
    - 1 letter, J. C. Squire to Cyril. Clemens, 1936 (Box 2)
    - 9 letters, Katharine E. Symons (Sister of A. E. HI.) to Cyril Clemens, 1936-42 (including 3 postcards) (Box 2)
    - 3 letters, Percy Withers to Cyril. Clemens, 1936-37 (Box 2)
- Series II: Other Materials
  - Subseries II.1: D. Manuscripts (12)
    - Clemens, Cyril.."Death"' (chapter of projected biogr. of A. E. H.) With corrections and notes by Katharine E. Symons--see correspondence) (Box 2)
    - Clemens, Cyril. "Oxford" (chapter of projected biography of A. E. H.) With corrections by J. T. Nance and attached notes by Katharine E. Symons-see correspondence). (Box 2)
    - Dunsany, Lord. "A. E. Housman". 4 line verse.. author's holograph. (Box 2)
    - Housman, A. E. [List of numbers (pages?, copies?) (Box 2)
    - Housman, Laurence. Galley proof, with author's ms. Corrections, signed (Box 2)
    - Housman, Laurence. List of books (Box 2)
    - Housman, Laurence. Tear-sheet of auction catalog, with L.D's notes, Signed (Box 2)
    - Housman, Laurence."The Mote and Beam" 12.line poem,. Signed (Box 2)
    - Housman, Laurence. "The Shropshire Lad". Year and After, signed (Box 2)
    - Housman, Laurence. "There is no Death" 12 line poem, signed (Box 2)
    - Rothenstein, Sir William. [excerpt] From Men and Memories. Handwriting of Percy Withers? (Box 2)
    - Whicher" George Meason. "An Interview with Housman". Signed by author (Box 2)
  - Subseries II.2: E. Miscellaneous (4 primary pieces)
    - Photograph" A. E. Housman in Laurence Housman’s rose garden (Box 2)
    - Photograph, A. E. Housman’s grave and plaque (Box 2)
    - Printed piece: Percy Withers" "A.. E. Housman"" July" 1936 (Box 2)
    - Printed piece: Katharine Symons ''More Memories of A.E.H.", 1936 (Box 2)
    - General: 4 items, mainly sent to Cyril Clemens by Laurence Housman (Box 2)
    - Clippings and Folders, various (Box 2)